

Mitesh Chakma

SUMMARY

Software Engineer with 4 years of experience in Python and leading tech projects. Successfully enhancing systems and developing solutions both in-house and remotely, currently working with Turing. Pursuing an MSc in Software Engineering to further deepen expertise.

SKILLS

- Programming Language: Python
- Web Technologies: HTML, CSS, JS
- Big Data & Data Engineering: Databricks, PySpark
- Database: MySQL, PostgreSQL, MongoDB

- Version Control: Git, Jira, Bitbucket, Trello
- Development & Operation: AWS S3, Docker
- Machine Learning Technologies: Scikit-learn, Feature Engineering, ML Modeling and Algorithm development

WORK EXPERIENCES

January 2023 -Present

Al Trainer | TURING | Silicon Valley, California, United States | Remote

- Prepared datasets, implemented ETL, built pipelines, performed quality checks, optimized databases, and automated validation for AI training.
- Assisted in the development and training of AI models using various machine learning techniques, regularly evaluating and validating model performance.
- Optimized database performance and storage solutions, leveraging technologies like SQL, NoSQL, and cloud-based data platforms to enhance data retrieval and manipulation efficiency.

December 2020 -December 2022

Software Engineer | FernTech Solutions Ltd. | Dhaka, Bangladesh

- Led the project "HnCitiPages" targeting the South African market.
- Designed the core backend of the application and implemented aligned solutions.
- Enhanced backend functionalities and boosted site upload capacity, thereby amplifying user feedback.

July 2020 -November 2020

Software Engineer | SK JAPAN EXPORT CO. LTD | Dhaka, Bangladesh

- Collaborated with AI engineers and frontend developers to deploy solutions on shared platforms.
- Developed new web functionality and managed AI models on the IOT platform.
- Designed single sign-on with Identity and Access Management using KeyCloak.
- Trained, managed, and guided Intern software development engineers.

October 2018 -May 2018

Trainee Artificial Intelligence Engineer | Hiperdyne Corporation | Dhaka, Bangladesh

- Developed algorithms using Python, NumPy, and Pandas for data filtering.
- Visualized data through graphs and charts for meaningful interpretation.
- Implemented data mining strategies to curate a valuable database.

June 2018 -September 2018

Research Assistant | LASET, BRAC University, Dhaka, Bangladesh

- Processed and visualized environmental and social geospatial data for Bangladeshi urban and rural areas.
- Utilized ArcGIS to conduct specialized spatial analysis, improving data visualization with detailed graphs and charts.
- Constructed a machine-learning script to predict future growth in urban and rural regions of Bangladesh.

Education

2023 - Present 2013 - 2017 MSc in Software Engineering | Lappeenranta University of Technology, Lappeenranta, Finland BSc in Computer Science | BRAC University, Dhaka, Bangladesh

August 2016 -December 2016 **Exchange Student, Computer Science | Kent State University, OH, USA |** Administered by: World Learning Sponsored by: US Department of State's Bureau of Educational and Cultural Affairs

Publications

PUBLICATION 1:

"Determining Land Use and Land Cover Changes and Predicting the Growth of Dhaka, Bangladesh Using Remote Sensing and GIS Techniques", Malaysia, ICESSAT2018

URL:https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/1742-6596/1152/1/012023

PUBLICATION 2:

"Change Detection of the Sundarban Part of Bangladesh Using Remote Sensing and GIS Techniques with Machine Learning Algorithms", Germany, IAC 2018

URL:https://iafastro.directory/iac/paper/id/47723/summary/